George S. McGovern Papers Series 5: Audiovisual Materials, 1957-1984 (bulk 1968-1972 )
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
George S. McGovern Papers Series 5: Audiovisual Materials
1957-1984
1968-1972
MC181.05
Princeton University Library. Special Collections. Seeley G. Mudd Manuscript Library. Public Policy Papers. 65 Olden Street Princeton, New Jersey 08540 USA
105.92 linear feet in 111 boxes Approximately 1,786 items
McGovern, George S. (George Stanley), 1922-2012
The Audiovisual Materials series documents McGovern's political activities from 1957-1984. It contains film footage, video recordings, audiotapes and audiocassettes, computer tapes and diskettes, and other formats. It is the only series in this collection that includes material for the years 1981-1984.
George Stanley McGovern (1922-2012) was a United States American senator and Democratic presidential nominee known for his strong liberal stance. The second of four children, he was born in Avon, South Dakota, in 1922 to Joseph C. McGovern, a Wesleyan Methodist pastor, and Frances McGovern (née McLean). George McGovern enrolled at Dakota Wesleyan University in Mitchell, S.D., in 1940. While at Dakota Wesleyan, he joined the Dakota Wesleyan Varsity Debate Squad, winning the South Dakota Intercollegiate Oratory Contest in 1941 and the Red River Valley Tournament in 1943.
McGovern earned a pilot's license through the Civilian Pilot Training Program and enlisted in the Air Force following the attacks on Pearl Harbor. He began training in February, 1943, and was deployed in the fall of 1944 to an airbase near Cerignola in Northern Italy. In the following ten months preceeding his discharge in July 1945, he flew 35 bomber missions with B-24 Liberators over targets in Europe, including Linz, Vienna, and Munich, as well as a number of food relief flights following the surrender of Germany. In honor of his wife Eleanor, he named any plane he piloted the "Dakota Queen," a practice he later extended to his campaign planes. McGovern was awarded the Air Medal for heroism in battle.
Returning to Dakota Wesleyan in 1945 to finish his studies under the G.I. Bill, McGovern earned his B.A. in 1946 and went on to study divinity at the Garrett Theological Seminary in Evanston, Illinois. Dissatisfied with the ministry, he enrolled at Northwestern University, earning his M.A. in History in 1949. He returned to Dakota Wesleyan as a professor of history and political science while also continuing his studies with Arthur S. Link at Northwestern. In 1953, he received his Ph.D. in history with his dissertation, "The Colorado Coal Strike, 1913-1914".
Though raised a Republican, McGovern became a supporter of Henry Wallace, serving as a delegate from Illinois for the Progressive Party Convention in Philadelphia in 1948. In 1952, Adlai Stevenson's acceptance speech following his nomination as the Democratic presidential candidate moved McGovern to register as a Democrat. He left Dakota Wesleyan the following year to become the executive secretary of the Democratic Party in South Dakota and spent the following years revitalizing the party's presence in the traditionally conservative state.
In 1956, McGovern successfully ran for Congress and became the United States Representative for the First District of South Dakota, winning reelection against Joe Foss in 1958. During his four years in the House of Representatives, McGovern served on the Committee on Education and Labor and on the Committee on Agriculture, where he advocated strongly for rural development, food stamp legislation, and foreign food aid. These themes would characterize his subsequent political career.
McGovern challenged Karl Mundt for his Senate seat in 1960. Though the campaign focused on rural issues, McGovern's political ties to Robert and John F. Kennedy, whose Catholic background was unpopular in South Dakota, ultimately contributed to his defeat. In a phone call to his brother at the time, John F. Kennedy said "I think we just cost that nice guy a Senate seat," and subsequently offered McGovern a position in his administration as Special Assistant to the President.
In that function, McGovern served as the director of the Food for Peace Program from January 1961-July 1962. During that time, McGovern leveraged the agricultural surplus of the U.S., which had frequently been viewed as a problem since it lowered farm profits, to alleviate world hunger and improve foreign relations. When McGovern left office to run again for the Senate, Food for Peace was operating in twelve countries.
In 1962, McGovern won a Senate seat against Joseph Bottum, who had been appointed following Francis Case's unexpected death earlier that year. He was subsequently reelected in 1968 and 1974 and served in the Senate until 1981. When McGovern joined the 88th Congress in 1963, he joined the Committee on Agriculture and Forestry and the Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs and from the start developed a strong stance on farm prices, rural development, and food programs. After 1967, when he assumed the chairmanship of the Subcommittee on Indian Affairs, McGovern also became an outspoken advocate for the rights of Native Americans and for improving education and employment opportunities on the reservations. In addition, McGovern consistently challenged military and defense spending, a position that correlated with his opposition to the war in Vietnam and which became one of his central tenets. In 1969, McGovern became the chairman of the newly created Select Committee on Nutrition and Human Needs and, in 1978, of its successor, the Subcommittee on Nutrition. The committee played a major role in developing legislation for food stamp and school lunch programs, and explored the relationship between nutrition and health. In 1977, the Select Committee issued a seminal report, Dietary Goals for the United States (known as the "McGovern Report"), which advocated a decrease in the consumption of fats and refined sugars, and an increase in the consumption of complex carbohydrates and fiber. The report is the precursor of today's Dietary Guidelines for Americans.
McGovern campaigned briefly for the Democratic presidential nomination in 1968 following the assassination of Robert Kennedy, announcing his candidacy on August 10 and losing the nomination to Hubert Humphrey during the Democratic National Convention in Chicago three weeks later. At the convention, a motion was passed to establish the Commission on Party Structure and Delegate Selection, of which McGovern became the chairman when it began work in 1969. The commission significantly strengthened the role of caucuses and primaries and set quotas for women, youth, and minority delegates.
In 1972, McGovern won his party's nomination and ran for president against Richard Nixon on a platform that emphasized withdrawal from Vietnam and more equitable social welfare programs. While McGovern had been able to attract an enthusiastic following during the primaries partly based on his perception as an idealistic, anti-establishment candidate, his campaign was damaged by the discovery that his vice-presidential candidate, Senator Thomas Eagleton, had a history of psychiatric illness. Eagleton's removal from the ticket was viewed by many voters as political opportunism, causing the campaign to lose substantial support. In addition, the campaign lost momentum when the Nixon administration reduced troop levels in Vietnam, thereby deflating one of McGovern's main campaign issues. In addition, McGovern represented the left wing of the Democratic Party and was unable to attract the support of moderates. Given these factors combined with the power of incumbency wielded by his opponent, McGovern lost in a landslide to Richard Nixon, carrying only the state of Massachusetts.
In 1980, McGovern lost his Senate reelection bid in the course of the "Reagan Revolution" that swept many Democrats from office. He subsequently ran unsuccessfully for the Democratic presidential nomination in 1984 against (among others) Jesse Jackson, Walter Mondale, and Gary Hart, who had been his campaign manager in 1972. He considered a renewed attempt for the nomination in 1992 but ultimately decided against it, deferring to the wishes of his family.
After electoral politics, McGovern continued to work to alleviate world hunger, serving as U.S. ambassador to the United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization and on the board of the Friends of the World Food Program. In 2001, he was appointed the United Nations Global Ambassador on World Hunger. He received the Presidential Medal of Freedom in 2000.
George McGovern was married to Eleanor Stegeberg McGovern (1921-2007). The couple had five children: Ann, Steven, Susan, Mary, and Terry (Teresa), who died 1994 from exposure related to alcohol addiction. Her death prompted George McGovern to author the book Terry: My Daughter's Life-and-Death Struggle with Alcoholism and to help create the Teresa McGovern Center, a non-profit treatment facility for substance abuse patients.
George McGovern died on October 21, 2012 at age 90.
George McGovern authored or co-authored numerous books, including the following selection:
War Against Want: America's Food for Peace Program (1964)
Agricultural Thought in the Twentieth Century (1966)
A Time of War--A Time of Peace (1968)
The Great Coalfield War (1972)
The Third Freedom: Ending Hunger in Our Time (2002)
The Essential America: Our Founders and the Liberal Tradition (2004)
Out of Iraq: A Practical Plan for Withdrawal Now (2006)
Abraham Lincoln (2008)
The Audiovisual Materials Series documents George McGovern's political career, including his years in the House of Representatives 1956-1960 (no materials dating from 1956), his service as Special Assistant to the President, in which function he directed the Food for Peace Program (1961-1962), and his senatorial career (1962-1981). In addition, the series contains campaign materials from McGovern's House and Senate campaigns as well as his 1972 presidential campaign and his unsuccessful bids for the Democratic presidential nomination in 1968 and 1984. The material dating from 1981-1984 is of particular interest as no other series of the George S. McGovern Papers document this time period. The series contains film footage, video recordings, audiotapes and audiocassettes, computer tapes and diskettes, and other formats.
This series is organized chronologically for dated material and alphabetically for undated material. In addition, each item has been assigned an item number, which precedes the item title. Multiple item numbers preceding a title indicate the presence of multiple copies and/or a multi-part item. Unidentified material is filed at the end of the series by item number.
The series is organized into the following subseries:
The collection is open for research.
The Audiovisual Materials series, 1957-1984 (bulk 1968-1972) is part of the George S. McGovern Papers (MC181). A complete finding aid for the McGovern Papers can be found here: George McGovern Papers.
The bulk of the papers were donated to the Princeton University Library in 1977, 1981, and 1987.
Several smaller accruals were received over the years as follows:
By the University of Mississippi in 2006 ([ML.2006.015]); by the Archives at the Alaska and Polar Regions Department, Elmer E. Rasmuson Library, University of Alaska Fairbanks, in 2007 ([ML.2007.008]); by the United States Senate Historical Office in 2008 ([ML.2008.018]); by David Gerber in 2009 ([ML.2009.010]).
A McGovern presidential campaign film was donated by Christopher Buchanan in 2013 ([ML.2014.020]). Two previously unprocessed boxes were discovered by the Mudd Library in 2014 and added to the collection ([ML.2014.034]).
A total of 809 linear feet of materials were separated from the collection in 2009 as follows: 20 linear feet of books (sent to Firestone Library and the Special Collections for further processing); 123 linear feet of redundant constituent correspondence (a 6% sample of which was retained); 59 linear feet of secondary material available from other sources (destroyed); 144 linear feet of routine constituent correspondence (destroyed); 35 linear feet of routine office files (destroyed); 101 linear feet of duplicate correspondence carbons (destroyed); 106 linear feet of clippings available from other sources (destroyed); 50 linear feet of duplicates (destroyed); 53 linear feet of material, including card files and contribution envelopes, that duplicates information available elsewhere in the collection (destroyed); 103 linear feet of case files peripheral to policy research (destroyed); 4 linear feet of book drafts peripheral to policy research (destroyed); 9 linear feet of personal records peripheral to policy research (destroyed); and 2 linear feet of blank forms and folders of no research value (destroyed).
Additional papers of Senator McGovern are housed at the McGovern Library at Dakota Wesleyan University in Mitchell, SD. An online finding aid is available here: The Senator George S. McGovern Collection.
Ambrose, Stephen. The Wild Blue: The Men and Boys Who Flew the B-24s Over Germany. New York: Simon and Schuster, 2001.
Campaign '72: The Managers Speak. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1973.
Marano, Richard Michael. Vote Your Conscience: The Last Campaign of George McGovern. Westport, Conn. and London: Praeger, 2003.
McGovern, George. Grassroots: The Autobiography of George McGovern. New York: Random House, 1977.
McGovern, George. An American Journey: The Presidential Campaign Speeches of George McGovern. New York: Random House, 1974.
Miroff, Bruce. The Liberals’ Moment: The McGovern Insurgency and the Identity Crisis of the Democratic Party. Lawrence, Kan.: University Press of Kansas, 2007.
Stephen, Vittoria (writer/director). One Bright Shining Moment: The Forgotten Summer of George McGovern (videorecording). 2005.
Thompson, Hunter S. Fear and Loathing: On the Campaign Trail '72. New York and Boston: Grand Central Publishing, [1983] 2006.
Watson, Robert P., ed. George McGovern: A Political Life, a Political Legacy. Pierre, South Dakota: South Dakota State Historical Society Press, 2004.
McGovern, George S. (George Stanley) 1922-; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous) 1913-1994 --Political and social views.; Kennedy family.; Eagleton, Thomas F., 1929-2007.; McGovern, Eleanor, 1921-2007.; Shriver, Sargent, 1915-; Elections -- United States -- 20th century.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1972.; Campaign literature, 1972 -- Democratic.; Campaign speeches, 1972 -- Democratic.; Democratic Party (U.S.).; Liberalism -- United States.; Political campaigns -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Presidential candidates -- United States -- Biography.; Legislators -- United States -- Biography.; United States. Congress. Senate.; Campaign speeches, 1972 -- Democratic.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Transcripts.; Negatives (photographic).; Politicians -- United States.; presidential candidates -- United States.; American history/20th century; American politics and government; Cold War
- Series 5: Audiovisual Materials, 1957-1984; 105.42 linear feet 110 boxes Approximately 1,785 items
  Series 5 documents a major portion of George McGovern's political career, including most years in the House of Representatives (1957-1960), his service as Special Assistant to the President and director of the Food for Peace Program (1961-1962), and his senatorial career (1962-1981). In addition, the series contains campaign materials from McGovern's House and Senate campaigns as well as his 1972 presidential campaign and his unsuccessful bids for the Democratic presidential nomination in 1968 and 1984. The material dating from 1981-1984 is of particular interest as no other series of the George S. McGovern Papers documents this time period. The series contains film footage, video recordings, audiotapes and audiocassettes, computer tapes and diskettes, and other formats.
  Subseries 5A: 1957-1959
  Subseries 5B: 1960-1969
  Subseries 5C: 1970-1979
  Subseries 5D: 1980-1984
  Subseries 5E: Undated Materials, undated
  Subseries 5F: Unidentified Materials, undated
  - Subseries 5A, 1957-1959 September 14; 5 linear feet one box
    This subseries contains audiovisual materials from McGovern's early political career in the House of Representatives. Of special interest are McGovern's statements on policy as well as speeches from his 1958 reelection campaign to the House.
    Subseries 5A is arranged chronologically.
    - Hubert Humphrey Fundraising Meeting, 1957; 1113; portion of 1 box (Box 789)
      Box number provided 874 incorrect
    - McGovern in Rome, 1957 April 28; 357; portion of 1 box (Box 789)
    - Huron, Senator John F. Kennedy, 1958; 919; portion of 1 box (Box 789)
    - Jefferson-Jackson Day Dinner, 1958 April 12; portion of 1 box (Box 789)
      Includes materials with identifiers: 354, 361, 362.
    - Labor Reform Bill, 1958 August 5; 336; portion of 1 box (Box 789)
    - KBRK Radio, Brooking, South Dakota, 1958 September 23; 1440; portion of 1 box (Box 789)
    - Antesian, South Dakota Speech, 1958 October 1; 918; 1 box (Box 789)
    - Last Campaign Address, 1958 October 30; portion of 1 box (Box 789)
      Includes materials with identifiers: 326, 339, 341.
    - Speech, 1958 October 30; 1114; portion of 1 box (Box 789)
    - Mcormack, 1959 February 5; 121; 16mm portion of 1 box (Box 789)
    - McGovern #599, 1959 April 20; 120; 16mm 1 box (Box portion of 789)
    - 1959 April 27, 123; 16mm portion of 1 box (Box 789)
    - 1959 June 13, 124; 16mm portion of 1 box (Box 789)
    - McGovern #1099, 1959 June 18; 112; 16mm portion of 1 box (Box 789)
    - 1959 June 26, 122; 16mm portion of 1 box (Box 789)
    - Broadcast to South Dakota, presidential Budget for 1961, 1959 September 14; portion of 1 box (Box 789)
      Includes materials with identifiers: 324, 325.
  - Subseries 5B, 1960 January 20-1969 December 17; 14.5 linear feet 14 boxes
    This subseries contains audiovisual materials from McGovern's unsuccessful 1960 Senate campaign, his time as the director of the Food for Peace Program, his successful 1962 and 1968 Senate campaigns, and his 1968 bid for the Democratic presidential nomination. Noteworthy items include the South Dakota visits of Bobby and Teddy Kennedy as well as the 1968 Democratic National Convention.
    Subseries 5B is arranged chronologically.
    - Report From Congress, Discussion with Quentin Burdick, Blackwater Navigation Charter, 1960 January 20; 323; 1 box (Box 789)
    - Robert Kennedy in South Dakota #35, 1960 January 27; 1015; 1 box (Box 789)
    - Statement Following Election of Quentin Burdick to fill Senate Seat, 1960 June 28; 555; 1 box (Box 789)
    - Taping of News Report in Chicago, 1961; 344; 1 box (Box 789)
    - McGovern Dictation During Hepatitis Illness, 1961 August-September; portion of 1 box (Box 789)
      Includes materials with identifiers: 345, 346.
    - Campaign Cuts, 1962; 340; 1 box (Box 789)
    - Senatorial Campaign, 1962; 347; 1 box (Box 789)
    - Opinion in the Capital with Mark Evans, 1962; 1105; 1 box (Box 789)
    - President JFK, Portion of State of the Union, 1962 January 11; 328; 1 box (Box 789)
    - President JFK, Remarks Following Defeat of the Medical Care for the Aged Bill, 1962 May 9; 329; 1 box (Box 789)
    - President Kennedy #6, 1962 September 26; 1141; 2 minutes 14 seconds (Box 789)
    - Secretary Freeman, Winner South Dakota, 1962 September 30; 1098; 1 box (Box 789)
    - Hubert Humprey's Watertown Speech, 1962 October 17; 1159; 1 box (Box 789)
    - Thanksgiving Spot, 1962 November 26; 1139; 16mm 1 box (Box 789)
    - American Newspaper Women's Club, 1963 January 6; 353; 1 box (Box 789)
    - TV and Radio Spots, 1963 January 22; 1698; 1 box (Box 789)
    - Wheat Referendum, 1963 March 19; 338; 1 box (Box 789)
    - McGovern Remarks on the Introduction of his Wheat Bill, 1963 July 29; 193; 16mm 1 box (Box 789)
    - Excerpt-The Tris Coffin Show, 1963 August 21; 948; 1 box (Box 789)
    - Jefferson-Jackson Day Dinner, Rapid City, South Dakota, 1963 September 27; 921; 1 box (Box 789)
    - McGovern-Freeman, 1964; 494; 16mm 1 box (Box 789)
    - McGovern-Crow and Graves, South Dakota Indian Problems, 1964; 526; 16mm 1 box (Box 790)
    - McGovern-Anderson, 1964; 527; 16mm 1 box (Box 790)
    - 1964 February 20, 1441; 1 box (Box 790)
    - KOTA Radio Television, 1964 March 6; 1730; 16mm 1 box (Box 790)
    - Graves and Crow, 1964 March 6; 1731; 16mm 1 box (Box 790)
    - Senator Ted Kennedy, Corn Palace Speech, 1964 April 13; 920; 1 box (Box 790)
    - Senator Church, 1964 May 1; 1096; 1 box (Box 790)
    - McGovern-Holum, Educational Material, 1964 June 8; 1732; 16mm 1 box (Box 790)
    - Johnson-Humphrey Ticket, 1964 October 28; 1424; 16mm 1 box (Box 790)
    - Ellsworth Air Force Base, 1964 October 30; 335; 1 box (Box 790)
    - Campaign Film Brought Back from State Headquarters by George Cunningham, 1964 November 13; 1143; 16mm 1 box (Box 791)
    - Various Selections, 1964 December 30; 368; 1 box (Box 792)
    - CBS Radio Program Capital Cloakroom, 1965 February 4; 348; 1 box (Box 792)
    - Voice of America: JFK Ceremonies, 1965 May 20; 367; 1 box (Box 792)
    - CBS Capital Cloakroom, McGovern-McGee on Vietnam, 1965 July 21; 350; 1 box (Box 792)
    - 1965 September 13, 1045; 2 minutes 38 seconds (Box 792)
    - Voice of America: Food for Peace Speech, 1965 September 24; 377; 1 box (Box 792)
    - Oahe Spot, 1965 October 4; 1140; 1 minute 43 seconds (Box 792)
    - Voice of America: Arrival of Senator McGovern, Tower, and R. McNamara, 1965 December 6; 1095; 1 box (Box 792)
    - McGovern Recognition Dinner, 1965 December 16; 356; 1 box (Box 792)
    - Youth Wants to Know Telecast, Washington, D.C., 1965 December 22; 1148; 1 box (Box 792)
    - World Food Crisis and U.S. Foreign Policy, 1966; 1719-1720; reel 1 and 2 1 box (Box 792)
    - Reply from Lt. Col. Shale L. Tulin regarding Vietnam, 1967; 1681; 1 box (Box 792)
    - McGovern with William McMillan, Agricultural Programs, 1967; 1694; 1 box (Box 792)
    - Pancho, 1967; 474; 16mm 1 box (Box 889)
    - Senator McGovern, 1967 January 5; 1142; 1 minute 10 seconds (Box 792)
    - Garretson Newspaper, 1967 January 22; 1692; 16mm 1 box (Box 792)
    - A Year Towards Tomorrow, 1967 March 1; 461; 16mm 1 box (Box 793)
    - 1967 March 21, 986; 1 box (Box 794)
    - McGovern on Education Program Funding, 1967 April 5; 560; 1 box (Box 794)
    - Vietnam Debate, Depaul University with Senator Gale McGee, 1967 April 10; 349; 16mm 1 box (Box 794)
    - Black and White Negatives for 1968, 454; 16mm negative print) 1 box (Box 794)
    - McGovern for Senate 1968, 1028; 1 box (Box 794)
    - 1968 Campaign Cuts, 1021; 1 box (Box 794)
    - 1968 Convention, McGovern Nominations, 1019; 1 box (Box 794)
    - Kefauver-McGovern, 1968; 76; 16mm negative print) 1 box (Box 794)
    - Dr. Emil Holzhauser Campaign Spot, 1968; 337; 1 box (Box 794)
    - McGovern, 8 Cuts, 1968; 343; 1 box (Box 794)
    - Convention and Campaign, 1968; 442; 16mm 1 box (Box 794)
    - KOTA Radio-Television, McGovern Political Material, 1968; 463; 16mm 1 box (Box 795)
    - McGovern Senate Campaign, 1968; 599; 1 box (Box 796)
    - McGovern Indians, 1968; 698; 13 minutes 30 seconds (Box 796)
    - Broadcast to South Dakota, 1968; 978; 1 box (Box 796)
    - McGovern Spots #1-11, 1968; 1022; 1 box (Box 796)
    - Eleanor McGovern Interview, 1968 Democratic Convention, 1034; 1 box (Box 796)
    - News Tape with Sander Vanocur, 1968; 1035; 1 box (Box 796)
    - McGovern for Senate #1-7, 1968; portion of 1 box (Box 796)
      Includes materials with identifiers: 1092, 1093, 1094.
    - Pat McKeever, 1968; 1329; 1 box (Box 796)
    - Prairie Statesman, 1968; 477; 16mm portion of 1 box (Box 891)